<section xmlns="http://xml.house.gov/schemas/uslm/1.0" style="-uslm-lc:I80" id="rp-18e7327270ed4cee7da9" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161">
  <num value="3161">§ 3161.</num>
  <heading> Time limits and exclusions</heading>
  <subsection style="-uslm-lc:I11" class="indent0" id="rp-a28ae05683f786d6b73a" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/a">
    <num value="a">(a)</num>
    <heading>Trial on a day certain</heading>
    <content> In any case involving a defendant charged with an offense, the appropriate judicial officer, at the earliest practicable time, shall, after consultation with the counsel for the defendant and the attorney for the Government, set the case to begin trial on a day certain, so as to assure a speedy trial.</content>
  </subsection>
  <subsection style="-uslm-lc:I11" class="indent0" id="rp-bddaee95790c3808d53a" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/b">
    <num value="b">(b)</num>
    <heading>Time to trial</heading>
    <paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="rp-de4de19cf774b248d4b3" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/b/i">
      <num value="i">(i)</num>
      <content> In any case in which a plea of not guilty is entered, the trial of a defendant charged in an information or indictment with the commission of an offense shall commence within fifteen days from the filing date (and making public) of the information or indictment, or from the date the defendant has appeared before a judicial officer of the court in which such charge is pending, whichever date last occurs. If a defendant consents in writing to be tried before a magistrate judge on a complaint, the trial shall commence within fifteen days from the date of such consent.</content>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="rp-7364a01425c7da987662" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/b/ii">
      <num value="ii">(ii)</num>
      <content> Unless the defendant consents in writing to the contrary, the trial shall not commence less than five days from the date on which the defendant first appears through counsel or expressly waives counsel and elects to proceed pro se.</content>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="rp-c46bc9bbe5794d31924e" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/b/iii">
      <num value="iii">(iii)</num>
      <content> If the defendant is to be tried upon an indictment or information dismissed by a trial court and reinstated following an appeal, the trial shall commence within fifteen days from the date the action occasioning the trial becomes final.</content>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="rp-4f360224f9d4786d1252" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/b/iv">
      <num value="iv">(iv)</num>
      <content> If the defendant is to be tried again following a declaration by the trial judge of a mistrial or following an order of such judge for a new trial, or the defendant is to be tried again following an appeal, the trial shall commence within fifteen days from the date the action occasioning the retrial becomes final.</content>
    </paragraph>
  </subsection>
  <subsection style="-uslm-lc:I11" class="indent0" id="rp-3d3b3ae76694527429e8" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/c">
    <num value="c">(c)</num>
    <heading>Periods of delay not included</heading>
    <chapeau> The following periods of delay shall be excluded in computing the time within which an information or an indictment must be filed, or in computing the time within which the trial of any such offense must commence:</chapeau>
    <paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="rp-b99192cd9a88b1082c62" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/c/i">
      <num value="i">(i)</num>
      <chapeau> Any period of delay resulting from other proceedings concerning the defendant, including but not limited to—</chapeau>
      <subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I13" class="indent2" id="rp-ba928d3daba7a2c78a64" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/c/i/1">
        <num value="1">(1)</num>
        <content> delay resulting from holiday periods;</content>
      </subparagraph>
      <subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I13" class="indent2" id="rp-8de6997977e23f45445d" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/c/i/2">
        <num value="2">(2)</num>
        <content> delay resulting from any interlocutory appeal;</content>
      </subparagraph>
      <subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I13" class="indent2" id="rp-8fcdd5383a0686d8ef0e" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/c/i/3">
        <num value="3">(3)</num>
        <content> delay resulting from consideration by the court of a proposed plea agreement to be entered into by the defendant and the attorney for the Government; and</content>
      </subparagraph>
      <subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I13" class="indent2" id="rp-a899fa56abeaf067c7ea" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/c/i/4">
        <num value="4">(4)</num>
        <content> delay reasonably attributable to any period, not to exceed seven days, during which any proceeding concerning the defendant is actually under advisement by the court.</content>
      </subparagraph>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="rp-a248e3d917995b549453" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/c/ii">
      <num value="ii">(ii)</num>
      <content> Any period of delay during which prosecution is deferred by the attorney for the Government pursuant to written agreement with the defendant, with the approval of the court, for the purpose of allowing the defendant to demonstrate his good conduct.</content>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="rp-7a7b6f6d0258b7f33520" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/c/iii">
      <num value="iii">(iii)</num>
      <content> Any period of delay resulting from the absence or unavailability of the defendant or an essential witness.</content>
      <subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I13" class="indent2" id="rp-c2d01bda4c57633c6aff" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/c/iii/1">
        <num value="1">(1)</num>
        <content> For purposes of this paragraph, a defendant or an essential witness shall be considered absent when his whereabouts are unknown and, in addition, he is attempting to avoid apprehension or prosecution or his whereabouts cannot be determined by due diligence. For purposes of such subparagraph, a defendant or an essential witness shall be considered unavailable whenever his whereabouts are known but his presence for trial cannot be obtained by due diligence or he resists appearing at or being returned for trial.</content>
      </subparagraph>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="rp-5d1cf0042bc38db0ac88" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/c/iv">
      <num value="iv">(iv)</num>
      <content> Any period of delay resulting from a continuance granted by any judge on his own motion or at the request of the defendant or his counsel or at the request of the attorney for the Government, if the judge granted such continuance on the basis of his findings that the ends of justice served by taking such action outweigh the best interest of the public and the defendant in a speedy trial. No such period of delay resulting from a continuance granted by the court in accordance with this paragraph shall be excludable under this subsection unless the court sets forth, in the record of the case, either orally or in writing, its reasons for finding that the ends of justice served by the granting of such continuance outweigh the best interests of the public and the defendant in a speedy trial.</content>
      <subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I13" class="indent2" id="rp-9daed61c6337f130f69b" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/c/iv/1">
        <num value="1">(1)</num>
        <chapeau> The factors, among others, which a judge shall consider in determining whether to grant a continuance under this paragraph in any case are as follows:</chapeau>
        <clause style="-uslm-lc:I14" class="indent3" id="rp-b6bc58c8e9ee328dce44" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/c/iv/1/a">
          <num value="a">(a)</num>
          <content> Whether the failure to grant such a continuance in the proceeding would be likely to make a continuation of such proceeding impossible, or result in a miscarriage of justice.</content>
        </clause>
        <clause style="-uslm-lc:I14" class="indent3" id="rp-cdc949d50e70893e00ff" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/c/iv/1/b">
          <num value="b">(b)</num>
          <content> Whether the case is so unusual or so complex, due to the number of defendants, the nature of the prosecution, or the existence of novel questions of fact or law, that it is unreasonable to expect adequate preparation for pretrial proceedings or for the trial itself within the time limits established by this section.</content>
        </clause>
        <clause style="-uslm-lc:I14" class="indent3" id="rp-7ebc06d20574c7133bf8" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/c/iv/1/c">
          <num value="c">(c)</num>
          <content> Whether the failure to grant such a continuance in a case which, taken as a whole, is not so unusual or so complex as to fall within clause (b), would deny the defendant reasonable time to obtain counsel, would unreasonably deny the defendant or the Government continuity of counsel, or would deny counsel for the defendant or the attorney for the Government the reasonable time necessary for effective preparation, taking into account the exercise of due diligence.</content>
        </clause>
      </subparagraph>
      <subparagraph style="-uslm-lc:I13" class="indent2" id="rp-235ac733d68efbd52bb9" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/c/iv/2">
        <num value="2">(2)</num>
        <content> No continuance under subparagraph (1) of this paragraph shall be granted because of general congestion of the court’s calendar, or lack of diligent preparation or failure to obtain available witnesses on the part of the attorney for the Government.</content>
      </subparagraph>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="rp-c2774002e771b58187ab" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3161/c/v">
      <num value="v">(v)</num>
      <content> If trial did not commence within the time limitation specified in this Act because the defendant had entered a plea of guilty or nolo contendere subsequently withdrawn to any or all charges in an indictment or information, the defendant shall be deemed indicted with respect to all charges on the day the order permitting withdrawal of the plea becomes final.</content>
    </paragraph>
  </subsection>
  <sourceCredit id="rp-76fd043080245d1e0b40">
    <ref href="/us/pl/38/266/s3">Pub. L. 38–266, § 3.</ref>
  </sourceCredit>
  <notes type="uscNote" id="rp-0d6ad53bb6808f7a7388">
    <note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="amendments" id="rp-317779c3202af897d58f">
      <heading class="centered smallCaps">USAR Amendments</heading>
      <p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0"><ref href="/us/pl/38/266/s3">Pub. L. 38–266, § 3</ref>, repealed and replaced former section 3161 as part of the replacement of chapter 208.</p>
    </note>
    <note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="effectiveDate" id="rp-f3413e4222ca524c22ae">
      <heading class="centered smallCaps">Effective Date; Nonretroactivity</heading>
      <p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0"><ref href="/us/pl/38/266/s8">Pub. L. 38–266, § 8</ref>, provided that the Act became effective upon enactment and that nothing in the Act shall be construed to apply ex post facto to any court case then ongoing in the United States District Court for the District of Columbia.</p>
    </note>
  </notes>
</section>
