<section xmlns="http://xml.house.gov/schemas/uslm/1.0" style="-uslm-lc:I80" id="rp-701fb3c14008b1ec105a" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3162">
  <num value="3162">§ 3162.</num>
  <heading> Sanctions</heading>
  <subsection style="-uslm-lc:I11" class="indent0" id="rp-1c85e986d25c37545547" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3162/a">
    <num value="a">(a)</num>
    <heading>Failure to bring to trial within time limit</heading>
    <content> If a defendant is not brought to trial within the time limits required by section 3 of this Act, the information or indictment shall be dismissed on motion of the defendant. The defendant shall have the burden of proof of supporting such motion but the Government shall have the burden of going forward with the evidence in connection with any exclusion of time. In determining whether to dismiss the case with or without prejudice, the court shall consider, among others, each of the following factors: the seriousness of the offense; the facts and circumstances of the case which led to the dismissal; and the impact of a reprosecution on the administration of this chapter and on the administration of justice. Failure of the defendant to move for dismissal prior to trial or entry of a plea of guilty or nolo contendere shall constitute a waiver of the right to dismissal under this section.</content>
  </subsection>
  <subsection style="-uslm-lc:I11" class="indent0" id="rp-0d7460790b3194f9c9a6" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3162/b">
    <num value="b">(b)</num>
    <heading>Failure to disclose factors</heading>
    <chapeau> In any case in which counsel for the defendant or the attorney for the Government</chapeau>
    <paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="rp-b3bfa6342de25647557d" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3162/b/1">
      <num value="1">(1)</num>
      <content> knowingly allows the case to be set for trial without disclosing the fact that a necessary witness would be unavailable for trial;</content>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="rp-039ce32526e93d618df1" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3162/b/2">
      <num value="2">(2)</num>
      <content> files a motion solely for the purpose of delay which he knows is totally frivolous and without merit;</content>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="rp-8bff0d8fca47961267a7" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3162/b/3">
      <num value="3">(3)</num>
      <content> makes a statement for the purpose of obtaining a continuance which he knows to be false and which is material to the granting of a continuance; or</content>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="rp-c70da6b03826ac9dd5cb" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3162/b/4">
      <num value="4">(4)</num>
      <content> otherwise willfully fails to proceed to trial without justification consistent with section 3161 of this chapter,</content>
    </paragraph>
    <continuation style="-uslm-lc:I17" class="indent1 firstIndent0"> the court may punish any such counsel or attorney, as follows:</continuation>
    <paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="rp-a342622986dae1c1cb4d" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3162/b/i">
      <num value="i">(i)</num>
      <content> in the case of an appointed defense counsel, by reducing the amount of compensation that otherwise would have been paid to such counsel pursuant to section 3006A of Title 18 in an amount not to exceed 25 per centum thereof;</content>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="rp-b5563a101effd251bd8b" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3162/b/ii">
      <num value="ii">(ii)</num>
      <content> in the case of a counsel retained in connection with the defense of a defendant, by imposing on such counsel a fine of not to exceed 25 per centum of the compensation to which he is entitled in connection with his defense of such defendant;</content>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="rp-6521b38850a055497449" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3162/b/iii">
      <num value="iii">(iii)</num>
      <content> by imposing on any attorney for the Government a fine of not to exceed $250;</content>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="rp-1d05a478e00b6e1b5e2a" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3162/b/iv">
      <num value="iv">(iv)</num>
      <content> by denying any such counsel or attorney for the Government the right to practice before the court considering such case for a period of not to exceed thirty days; or</content>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph style="-uslm-lc:I12" class="indent1" id="rp-0d26ea1bf44c25ca4393" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3162/b/v">
      <num value="v">(v)</num>
      <content> by filing a report with an appropriate disciplinary committee.</content>
    </paragraph>
    <continuation style="-uslm-lc:I17" class="indent1 firstIndent0"> The authority to punish provided for by this subsection shall be in addition to any other authority or power available to such court.</continuation>
  </subsection>
  <subsection style="-uslm-lc:I11" class="indent0" id="rp-07390cacad2e9aa07103" identifier="/us/usc/t18/s3162/c">
    <num value="c">(c)</num>
    <heading>Rules of procedure</heading>
    <content> The court shall follow procedures established in the Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure in punishing any counsel or attorney for the Government pursuant to this section.</content>
  </subsection>
  <sourceCredit id="rp-aaa7d7ffd3c8174e78ae">
    <ref href="/us/pl/38/266/s4">Pub. L. 38–266, § 4.</ref>
  </sourceCredit>
  <notes type="uscNote" id="rp-6295b9a63eb90333881f">
    <note style="-uslm-lc:I74" topic="amendments" id="rp-c4f7f53e87882571ab83">
      <heading class="centered smallCaps">USAR Amendments</heading>
      <p style="-uslm-lc:I21" class="indent0"><ref href="/us/pl/38/266/s4">Pub. L. 38–266, § 4</ref>, repealed and replaced former section 3162 as part of the replacement of chapter 208.</p>
    </note>
  </notes>
</section>
